Finding Aid for the American Art Association Records, 1877-1924 MS.15
The Frick Collection/Frick Art Reference Library Archives
American Art Association Records
1877-1924
MS.15
The Frick Collection/Frick Art Reference Library Archives
4.0 Linear feet (8 boxes)
The American Art Association, a New York art gallery and auction house, was founded in 1883 by James F. Sutton, R. Austin Robertson, and Thomas E. Kirby. The records date from 1877-1924, but the bulk of the material documents a selection of auction sales run by the gallery from 1910 through 1923. The collection contains correspondence, approximately 1,000 photographs, handwritten and typed notes, fragments of a typed manuscript on the American Art Association, and printed material.
American Art Association.
Kirby, Thomas E. (Thomas Ellis), 1846-1924.
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Thomas Waller (Wilhelmina), granddaughter of Thomas E. Kirby, 1956.
Separated Materials
Books and sales catalogues were removed and integrated into the Library's collection.
Related Materials
Twelve linear feet of scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings on auction sales require conservation attention and are not available for research due to their fragile condition.
American Art Association Records, 1853-1924. Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. (This collection contains the bulk of the American Art Association's records, an additional 50 linear feet)
Scope and Content Note
The American Art Association records document a selection of auction sales run by the gallery, as well as Thomas Kirby's relationship with those who sold their works through the American Art Association. Records date from 1877-1924, with the bulk dating from 1910-1924. The collection includes correspondence, approximately 1,000 photographs, handwritten and typed notes, fragments of a typed manuscript on the American Art Association, pages from auction sales catalogues, newspaper and periodical clippings, and several sales catalogues.
The bulk of the collection concerns specific auction sales conducted by the American Art Association. Files contain inventories of the works, often with prices and names of buyers; black and white photographs of the works and several of the exhibition installations; correspondence; sections of a typed manuscript on the American Art Association; handwritten notes regarding the sales; pages from sales catalogues; and clippings. Documentation of 70 sales ranges from a single typescript sentence to multiple folders of correspondence, inventories and hundreds of photographs of the items for sale. An additional 150 auction sales are represented in the files only by cursory handwritten notes. Some of the most heavily documented sales include 57 Paintings Belonging to Ichabod T. Williams of February 3-4, 1915;Charles of London, Italian, French & English Furniture, Tapestries, Rugs, Paintings, Porcelains, etc. of November 15-20, 1920; and Palatial Mansion & Contents Collected by William J. Saloman, April 4-7, 1923. Titles of sales were derived from the auction sales catalogue.
Also of note in the records is correspondence between Thomas Kirby and Arthur B. Emmons regarding several auctions in which works he owned were sold; 16 letters to Charles De Kay from correspondents other than Thomas Kirby; handwritten notes on George Inness; biographical comments on Thomas Kirby; a privately printed catalogue,Pictures in the Collection of F.A.G. Hood, Esq.; and several letters concerning the controversy over the authenticity of the painting Blue Boy at the William H. Fuller Sale of February 25, 1898, including a letter from Francis Davis Millet. A few clippings and letters document Kirby's career prior to his affiliation with the American Art Association.
Access Restrictions
These records are open for research under the conditions of The Frick Collection/Frick Art Reference Library Archives access policy. Contact the Archives Department for further information at archives@frick.org.
Arrangement
The records are organized in three series:
Series I: Auction Sales, 1910-1923
Series II: Correspondence and Notes, 1877-1924
Series III: Clippings, 1881-1924
Historical Note
The American Art Association, a New York art gallery and auction house, was founded by James F. Sutton, R. Austin Robertson, and Thomas E. Kirby in 1883. Exhibitions of American art, as well as some Asian decorative arts, were on display in the sales galleries at 6 East 23rd Street. Thomas Kirby acted as auctioneer for the firm.
Sutton and Robertson had previously established the American Art Gallery in 1879, which closed in 1882. Thomas Kirby had begun his career as an auctioneer in the early 1870s, working with a variety of firms, including George A. Leavitt and Company, and had conducted sales throughout the country. He had his own auction company, Thomas E. Kirby and Company, when he joined with Sutton and Roberts in 1883.
R. Austin Robertson died in 1892. Kirby's son Gustavus joined the firm in 1912 and became half owner in 1915, upon the death of James Sutton. The galleries moved to 30 East 57th Street in 1922. In 1923, Kirby retired and sold the American Art Association to Cortlandt Field Bishop (1870-1935), who contracted Hiram Parke and Otto Bernet to run the auction house. In 1929 it merged with the Anderson Auction Company to form the American Art Association-Anderson Galleries, Inc. In 1938, the firm was taken over by Parke-Bernet Galleries, Inc., which had been formed a year earlier.
Bolas, Gerald D.The Early Years of the American Art Association, 1879-1900. PhD diss., City University of New York, 1998.
American Art Association.; De Kay, Charles, 1848-1935.; Emmons, Arthur B.; Hood, G.F.W.; Kirby, Thomas E. (Thomas Ellis), 1846-1924.; Lorenz, Rose H., d. 1934--Clippings.; Art auctions--New York (State)--New York.; Art dealers--New York (State)--New York.; Art galleries, Commercial--New York (State)--New York.; Correspondence.; Newspaper clippings.; Painting--Prices.; Photographs.; Pictures in the Collection of F.A.G. Hood, Esq.
- Series I: Auction Sales, 1910-1923
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents note
  Documents selected auction sales conducted by the American Art Association. Contains file folder covers with handwritten notes, sections of a typed manuscript on the American Art Association that pertains to individual sales and sellers, inventories, price lists, correspondence, newspaper clippings, sales catalogues, and photographs of the works, including some installations. Also included are two files of biographical comments on Thomas Kirby from the American Art Association manuscript, which were numbered and originally interfiled with the Auction Sales records. Auction sales that are represented in the files with only cursory handwritten listings on the file folder cover are listed below as "Auction Sales" with a date range; the number in parentheses indicates the number of sales listed in the folder. Numbers following the folder title are those written on original folders.
  - Auction Sales (2), #368-369, 1910 Dec. 5-6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Modern Paintings, 1911 Jan. 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Note on original folder: "Private Collection of Paintings, John H. Converse, #370." Folder contains ten photographs, letter from John G. Johnson to Thomas Kirby, and inventory.
  - Rare and Beautiful Old Chinese Porcelains, Jades, etc. for...Yamanaka & Company, 1911 Jan. 5-7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Content Note
    Note on original folder: "Old Chinese Porcelain, Jades, etc., Yamanaka & Co., #371."
  - Comments, #371-A, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Typed biographical comments (four pages), primarily about Thomas Kirby and book sales.
  - Valuable Paintings Collected by the Late Dr. Leslie D. Ward of Newark, N.J./Barbizon Masters and Their Contemporaries, 1911 Jan. 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Note on original folder: "Dr. Leslie D. Ward, Valuable Paintings, #372." Folder contains 21 photographs.
  - Ancient and Modern Paintings and Other Objects of Art Collected by the Late William M. Laffan, 1911 Jan. 20-21 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Note on original folder: "Paintings & Objects of Art Collected by Wm. M. Laffan, #373." Folder contains letter from William Laffan to Thomas Kirby (May 24, 1903) containing comments about Mr. Morgan's visit to Aix-les-Bains, France during which he purchased no art.
  - Valuable modern paintings, 1911 Jan. 27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Note on original folder: "Valuable Modern Paintings, sold by the dealer Jules Oehme, #374."
  - Important Modern Paintings, 1911 Feb. 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Note on original folder: "Modern Paintings sold by order of Felix Isman, #375."
  - Comments, #376-A, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Typed biographical comments (two pages) on Mr. Kirby as the "premier auctioneer."
  - Auction Sales (2), #377-378, 1911 Mar. 6-7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Modern Paintings and Water Colors, 1911 Mar. 15-17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Note on original folder: "Modern Paintings & Water Colors, collected by late Peter A. Schemm, #379." Folder contains 40 photographs.
  - Auction Sales (3), #432-434, 1913 Nov. 5-10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Artistic Property of the Well Known House of Cottier and Company, New York, 1913 Nov. 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Note on original folder: "Artistic Property, Tapestries, Cottier & Company, #435."
  - Fine Old English Furniture...and Other Desirable Objects, 1913 Dec. 3-6 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Note on original folder: "Valuable Stock of Old English Furniture, Cooper & Griffith, #436." Folder contains letter from C.H. Griffith to the American Art Association (December 10, 1913) regarding his satisfaction with the outcome of the sale.
  - Antique and Modern Oriental Rugs and Carpets, and Other Beautiful Textiles, 1913 Dec. 8-10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Note on original folder: "Stock of Rugs & Textiles, John T. Keresey & Co., #437."
  - Auction Sales (2), #439-440, 1914 Jan. 15-16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notable Paintings by the Great Masters, 1914 Feb. 26-27 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Note on original folder: "Valuable Paintings, Collection by the Late Clement A. Griscom, #458." Folder contains 34 photographs.
  - Private Collection of Valuable Paintings by the Old Masters and Early English Artists Formed by the Late Leon Hirsch of New York/Remarkable Collection of Ancient Chinese Bronzes, Beautiful Old Porcelains ... Comprising the Private Collection of a Chinese Nobleman of Tien-Tsin and Objects Procured by the Senior Member of Messrs. Yamanaka & Co., 1914 Jan. 29-31 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Note on original folder: "Paintings by Old Masters & Early English School, Leon Hirsch, #441; Old Chinese Bronzes, Porcelains, Brocades, Paintings on Glass, Rugs and Furniture, Yamanaka & Co., #442." Folder contains four hand-tinted photographs and one black and white photo of objects in the auction, and five photographs of the exhibition rooms. (Five photographs were removed to Oversize box.)
  - Auction Sale (1), #433A, 1914 Feb. 5-9 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Antique Oriental Weaves of Rare and Distinctive Quality, Fine Old Persian Faiences, 1914 Jan. 6-9 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Note on original folder: "Old Oriental Weaves, Old Persian Faiences, Arm. Persian Looms and Other Oriental Treasures, O. Agopian & Son, #438."
  - Auction Sales (3) #434A, #436A, #437A; Horace Townsend, Famous Hargreave Collection of Wedgewood, Medallions, etc., #434B, 1914 Feb. 9-18 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Beautiful old Chinese porcelains Comprising the Extraordinary Private Collection Formed by Mr. S.S. Carvalho of New York/Finished Paintings, Drawings, and Studies Left by the Late Francis Davis Millet, N.A./Auction Sales (2), #440A-#441A, 1914 Feb. 24-Mar. 2; Mar. 6; Mar. 7-11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Note on original folder: "Great Collection of Blue and White Style Color Specimens, Peach Blooms, etc., S.S. Carvalho, #439A; Paintings & Drawings by the Late Francis Davis Millet, #442; Auction Sales (2), #440A-#441A." Folder cover also contains notes on Millet re Academy of Rome and his death.
  - Valuable Paintings by Foreign and American Masters, #443, 1914 Mar. 17-20 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Auction Sales (6), #444-449, 1914 Mar. 19- May 8 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Book Sales (16), 1913-1914, #400, 407-408, 451-457, 460-462, 468, 1913 Nov.- 1914 May (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Auction Sale (1), #466; Artistic & Other Property, Residence of Late Mrs. Emilie de L. Havermeyer, #467, 1914 Oct. 29 - Nov. 7; Nov. 16-23 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Essay "Monogram on the series 'Les fetes de Village' composed of three tapestries" (seven pages, typed), letter from John Getz to Kirby re Audran tapestries in sale (November 16, 1914), and three photographs of rooms in residence, two of tapestries.
    (2 photographs removed to Oversize box)
  - Auction Sale (1), #468; Old Chinese Rugs Collected by Thomas B. Clarke, #469, 1914 Dec. 3-7; 1915 Jan. 6-9 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Auction Sale (1), #470; Early English Portraits Collected by F.A.G. Hood, #471, 1915 Jan. 12-14; Jan. 21 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    Nine letters from G.F.W. Hood to Thomas Kirby, four telegrams, and 13 photographs. Also contains privately printed catalogue Pictures in the Collection of F.A.G. Hood, Esq. Catalogue contains some annotations.
  - Chinese & Japanese Bronzes Collected by Charles H. Cramps, #472; Auction sale (1), #473, 1915 Jan. 21; Jan. 19 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Tapestries, Old Laces, Snuff Boxes, Watches, Fans, Louis XV Furniture Collected by Duc d’Avaray, #474, 1915 Jan. 22-23 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Auction Sales (2), #475-476, 1915 Jan. 25 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 57 Paintings Belonging to Ichabod T. Williams, #477, 1915 Feb. 3-4 (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
    File folder cover with descriptive notes; two-page typed summary of sale with some buyers and prices listed; typed list of paintings with artist, number, buyer and price; and 123 photographs, with duplicates.
    (One file folder cover and 42 images removed to Oversize box)
  - Chinese Porcelains Collected by the late William Churchill Oestler, #479; Rare & Beautiful Art Treasures from China, Yamanaka, #480, 1915 Feb. 5-6; Feb. 16-17 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Auction Sale (1), #481, 1915 Feb. 25-27 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Valuable Oriental and Other Art Property, Arthur I. Hoe Collection, #482, 1915 Mar. 5-6 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Continuation Paintings Sale, various sellers, #483, 1915 Mar. 5 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Auction Sales (5), #484, 484A, 485-487, 1915 Mar. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Art and Literary Collections of the Late General Brayton Ives, #488, 1915 Apr. 6-14 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Correspondence (1910-1913) to General Brayton Ives from Edgar Gorer and Dreicer & Co., regarding the sale/purchase of his vases and other porcelains. Includes invoices with prices.
  - The Blakeslee Galleries of Paintings, #489, 1915 Apr. 21-22 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Letter to the American Art Association from Prinz Brothers denying any business dealings with Blakeslee, and copy of a confidential letter from John G. Johnson to Dr. Paul Mersch re strategy for selling the Blakeslee collection.
    (three photographs removed to Oversize box)
  - 15 Fine Paintings by the Great Masters, Duveen Brothers, "Fire Sale," #490, 1915 Apr. 29 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    File folder cover with notes about damage done to the paintings by a ship fire.
  - Chinese Porcelains, Jade, etc. belonging to Loo & Cie, #491; Auction Sale, #492, 1915 May 5-6; May 13 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Costly Church Treasures Belonging to the Dominican Order of the Catholic Church of Cuba, #493, 1915 Apr. 24- May 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Book Sales, 1914-1915, #494-504, 1914 Jul.-1915 May (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Costly Art Property & Antiquities Belonging to the House of Karl Freund, #526, 1916 Mar. 20-23 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Auction Sales (2), #563-564, 1916 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Old & Modern Paintings belonging to Several Estates, #593, 1917 Apr. 16-17 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Letter to Kirby regarding sales of pictures from Gustav Reichard Estate, and one photo.
  - Auction Sales (20), #594-612, 1917 Nov. - May (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Auction Sales (2), #686-687, 1919 Mar. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Textiles & Embroideries, V. Benguiat, #688, 1919 Apr. 7-12 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Auction Sale (1), #689, 1919 Apr. 15-16 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Old & Modern Masters, various sellers, #690, 1919 Apr. 24-25 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Art Treasures collected by the late Charles Stewart Smith, #691, 1919 Apr. 25-26 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Italian Renaissance Furniture, Bronzes, Ceramics, etc., Tolentino Galleries, #692, 1919 May 1-2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Auction Sales (2), #693-694, 1919 May (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Auction Sale (1): Books, #695; Sumptuous "Attic" Library of the late Alfred J. Cox, Master Binder, #696, 1918 Nov. 18-21; 1918 Dec. 9-10 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Auction Sales (8), (Book Sales) #697-704, 1918 Dec. - 1919 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Auction Sales (4), #706-709; Auction Sale: Residence of Arthur B. Emmons, 1919 Aug.-Nov.; 1919 Aug. 28 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    SEE ALSO: Correspondence and Notes -- Emmons, Arthur B.
  - Auction Sales (2), #710-711, 1919 Nov. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Furnishings & Embellishments, Residence of Captain J.R. De Lamar, #712, 1919 Nov. 20-22 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    (Eight photographs of residence interior removed to Oversize box)
  - Auction Sale (1), #713; Old & Modern Rugs & Carpets, #714, 1919 Nov.; 1919 Nov. 25 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Emil Pares, Spanish & Italian Furniture, Flemish & French Tapestries, etc., #715, 1919 Dec. 18-23 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Auction Sale (1), #716; Oriental Porcelain, Snuff Bottles, Vases, etc., Fred William Hunter, #717, 1919 Dec.; 1920 Jan. 7-14 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Old and Modern Paintings, Arthur B. Emmons., Thatcher B. Adams, Joseph F. Flanagan, Henry Sayles, Harris B. Dick, #718, 1920 Jan. 14-15 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
    43 photographs, and cuts from the catalogue marked with prices, size, number and seller.
    SEE ALSO: Correspondence and Notes - Emmons, Arthur B. for extensive correspondence regarding the sale.
  - Mrs. Rowland Lincoln and other Private Collections, #719, 1920 Jan. 22 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Mrs. Eben Sutton, Early American & English Furniture, Rare Glass, etc., #720, 1920 Jan. 22-24 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Furnishings & Embellishments, Mrs. James Brown, Mrs. Stephen Brown, Mrs. Lloyd Bryce, #721, 1920 Jan. 29-30 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Paintings collected by Capt. J.R. De Lamar, #722, 1920 Jan. 29 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    29 photographs.
  - Household Furniture, Tapestries, Clocks, etc. Thatcher M. Adams Estate, #723, 1920 Jan. 31 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Collection of Japanese Color Prints & Paintings, Arthur Davison Ficke, #724, 1920 Feb. 10-11 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Kouchakji Frères, Rare Persian Pottery, etc., #725, 1920 Feb. 13-14 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Ernest A. Bischoff Collection, Chinese Porcelain, etc., #726, 1920 Feb. 24-28 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Ralph H. White, Modern Paintings, #727, 1920 Feb. 25-26 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Paintings, Watercolors, Pastels, Drawings, Etchings, and Studio Effects of the late Hendrik William Mesdag, #728, 1920 Mar. 8-10 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Auction Sales (7), #729-735, 1920 Mar. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Auction Sale (1), #736; The Celebrated E. Eymonaud Collection and Vitall Benguiat Collection of Remarkable Rugs, Tapestries, & Textiles, #737, 1920 Mar. 29-30; 1920 Apr. 8-10 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - R. Hall McCormick, Portraits & Landscapes by British Masters, #738, 1920 Apr. 10 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
    80 photographs.
  - Early American & British Portraits, Landscapes & Historical Pictures, Frank Bulkeley Smith, #739, 1920 Apr. 22-23 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    99 photographs.
  - Italian Furniture, Tapestries, Bronzes, etc. collected by Raoul Tolentino, #740, 1920 Apr. 21-27 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Auction Sales (8), #741-748, 1919 Oct.-1920 May (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Auction Sale (1), #749; Late S.S. Rosenstamm, Masterpieces of Etchings, Notable Prints by Rembrandt & Durer, #750, 1920 Jan.; 1920 Jan. 27 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Auction Sale (1), #751; William Lanier Washington Relics & Memorabilia of George Washington, #752, 1920 Feb.; 1920 Feb. 7-9 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Auction Sales (6), #753-758, 1920 Feb.-Mar. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Auction Sales (9), #759-777, 1920 Mar.- May (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Charles of London, Italian, French & English Furniture, Tapestries, Rugs, Paintings, Porcelains, etc., #779, 1920 Nov. 15-20 (Box 4, Folder 10-13)
    182 photographs.
  - Auction Sale (1), #778; Antique French & Italian Furniture, Tapestries, Clocks, Laces & Velvets, Madame Lefortier, #780, 1920 Nov.; 1920 Dec. 2-4 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Auction Sale (1), #781; Beautiful English Lustre, Robert Gilchrist, #782, 1920 Dec.; 1920 Dec. 6-7 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Auction Sales (3), #782 (duplicate number), #784, 1920 Dec. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Palatial Mansion & Contents Collected by William J. Saloman, #950, 1923 Apr. 4-7
    - Correspondence, sale summaries and notes, 1912-1933 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      File folder cover; "Notes for Sir Joseph;" letters from Edwin S. Stuart, Jacques Seligmann and others; copies of letters from Joseph Duveen regarding the provenance of the works, his advice on the quality of the photographs, and suggestions that the paintings need to be cleaned (1912-1923); summaries listing some buyers, descriptions of the items in the sale, and prices; a note to Miss Lorenz; and, "A Short Summary of Some of the Outstanding Features Forming the Art Collection of Mr. William Saloman, Deceased" (five pages).
    - Inventories and Appraisals, 1922-1933 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      (One clipping removed to Oversize box)
    - Saloman Sales Catalogue tear sheets, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - Sales Catalogue tear sheets (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Marked-up tear sheets of items sold by Duveen Brothers and other dealers to Mr. Saloman.
    - Photographs - Furniture, Rugs, Tapestries (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
      91 photographs.
    - Photographs - Paintings (Box 6, Folder 1)
      32 photographs
    - Photographs - Sculpture & Decorative Objects (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
      117 photographs.
- Series II: Correspondence and Notes, 1877-1924
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or correspondent.
  Contains Thomas Kirby's correspondence regarding American Art Association auction sales, copies of letters pertaining to provenance, and miscellaneous notes and essays. Correspondents include Arthur B. Emmons, Francis Davis Millet, and William Fuller. Emmons correspondence concerns three American Art Association sales in which works he owned were sold. Also includes 16 letters sent to Charles de Kay from correspondents other than Thomas Kirby. Of note is an essay on the American Art Association's relationship with George Inness, and letters concerning the controversy over the sale of Blue Boy.
  - Blue Boy, William H. Fuller Sale (February 25, 1898) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Two letters from William Fuller, and one from Francis Davis Millet related to the sale of the painting Blue Boy.
  - "A Business Change" Notice, 1883 Feb. 17 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Notice re Thomas Kirby's sale of Thomas E. Kirby & Co. and his new association with James F. Sutton and R. Austin Robertson of The American Art Galleries and Art Association.
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1877-1898 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Three letters and one telegram. H. Harper (sp?) with regrets that Kirby is leaving Leavitt & Co. and response to request to use him as a reference; J.C. Hoagland regarding increasing value of Barbizon pictures; and letter from Kirby to Mr. [Aitken] with list of paintings to be omitted from his sale.
  - De Kay, Charles, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 8)